Praphul Samavedam

Data Scientist at UBS, Pune

in GitHub

praphulsamavedam@gmail.com

+(91)-9704120148

alteryx



Summary

Adept in data analytic skills with nearly 4 years of experience in business intelligence tools post under graduation from BITS-Pilani.

Skills

Machine Learning, Deep learning, Python, Alteryx (Adv. certified), Microsoft Azure, Tableau, SQL, Apache Spark

Experience

July 2018- Present Data Scientist

UBS, Pune

- Developed salesperson report dashboard for the new business division of global markets within 11 months using Alteryx, Tableau.
- Provided insights on the clients under different categories, which enhanced the relationship with clients by 6%
- Developed events dashboard for salespersons in Tableau, from incoming XML files processed using Python, Alteryx.
- 4 key performance indicators (KPIs) were migrated to Python using pandas library, which contributes to 26% of the calculation.
- Automated the refresh of the Python KPIs within a month, reducing 5 working-hours monthly.
- Lead the team towards Agile methodology increasing the productivity of the team by 12% based on lead-time.
- Introduced the Alteryx into the tech-stack of the team, thereby reducing the manual process time by nearly 20%.
- Campaign email automation for the campaign leads of Global Markets which increased the campaign coverage by 30%.

July-2017- Dec 2017

ARM compliance internship

Nvidia graphics, Bangalore

• Created a test plan and conducted bare metal tests for the newly added features of ARM v8.x like performance monitoring, Reliability, Availability and Serviceability(RAS) on the natively developed ARM, Denver simulators accounting to 93% coverage in 6months.

Jun 2016 - Jul 2016

Internet of things (IoT) internship (summer)

Pensio Tech, Hyderabad

• Transformer monitoring system, an IoT based JAVA application was developed within 2 months.

Research papers

EHHCW System Modeling and Outage Performance Analysis

IEEE CICT 2018, IIITDM Jabalpur

- First-ever energy harvesting hybrid co-operative wireless system (EHHCW System) consisting of a digital link and an analog link was developed and analyzed for outage probability and performance.
- Proposed strategies for further improvement of the performance by 15% and decrease in outage probability by 20%.

Academic background

Year: 2014-2018	B.E. (Hons) Electrical & Electronics Engineering	CGPA: 8.42/10	BITS-Pilani, Pilani
Year: 2012-2014	Intermediate – M.P.C.	Total : 976/1000	Narayana Intermediate College
Year: 2010-2012	Higher education - 10 th (School Topper)	CGPA: 9.80/10	Sri Chaitanya Techno School

Achievements

- Bagged 1st prize for "Transign" project under the AI category in the UBS Group Technology Superstars (an UBS internal event).
- Won center 1st in state-level mathematics talent test conducted by AIMED. (All India Mathematics Education)

Relevant mini projects

Meenutes - Summary of the meeting is transcribed and sent to the participants making meetings more effective by using speech recognition and natural language generation(NLG) Working prototype was developed within a day during a hackathon.

Lossless image compression and de-noising - Implemented curve-let transformation which provides 5% better PSNR & 15% better compression in MATLAB as a part of course work.

Leadership Capabilities

APOGEE joint coordinator

EEE Association, BITS-Pilani

• Successfully organized 2 kernel events namely R.A.W., i-Strike, and a massive workshop on track follower bot.

School coordinator

NSS. BITS-Pilani

• My team revamped the 70 volunteer's department which resulted in an increase in the average marks of students by 3.4% and 10th pass percentage by 12%.

Games/Sports

- School chess champion in 2010 after being runner up in 2007.
- Runner-up in intra-Nvidia football held from 5th September, 2017 to 26th September, 2017 during my internship at Nvidia.

Certifications: Access my certifications here